Finding Aid for the John Allison Benjamin Papers Biomed.0001
UCLA Library Special Collections
- II. RESEARCH, TEACHING, PATIENT CARE -- UROGENITAL SYSTEM
  - Dog reflux studies, x-ray movies, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    three manuscripts: 1. typescript of "The value of stereoscopic pneumopyelograms in the diagnosis and localization of renal and ureteral calculi," by W.W. Scott & JAB, two versions (see related reprint, Box 1-F14); 2. typescript and reprint of "Studies on the isolated dog ureter. The pharmacological action of histamine, levarterenol, and antihistaminics," by Philip S. Chen, Jr., Victor M. Emmel, JAB, Victor DiStefano; 3. two drafts and reprint of "Cinefluorographic studies of bladder and urethral function," by JAB et al.; 1956 annual report of James Picker Foundation for Radiological Research, listing JAB & J.S. Watson as grant recipients for cine studies; many pages of bibliographic notes & annotations; typed copies of part of a 1950 article on physiology of micturition, and from a 1680 (?) description of removing one kidney from living dogs [see Box 3-F24]; research notes, including lists of patients; notes for Pediatric Grand Rounds, 1957; list of past, present, and future research accomplishments of Dept. of Surgery, Division of Urology, [Univ. Rochester Medical School]; line drawings of aneurysm in renal artery [RESTRICTED]
  - "The prostatic smear: cell changes after estrogen therapy", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    reprint of an article by Hannah Peters and JAB, Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 91:660-668, Dec. 1950
  - "Observations on water diuresis and on ureteral peristalsis in an infant with exstrophy of the bladder", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    two typescripts and reprint of an article by Gertrude Falk and JAB submitted first to Journal of Clinical Investigation and then published in Surgery, Gynecology, and Obstetrics, with three mounted figures and pertinent correspondence; reprint also in Box 2-F30
  - "Treatment of prostatic hypertrophy", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    reprint of short article by JAB for Current Therapy for 1951, Philadelphia: Saunders. p. 331-333
  - "Abnormalities of the kidneys, ureters, and perinephric fascia: anatomic and clinical study", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    reprint and typed draft of an article by JAB and Charles E. Tobin, Journal of Urology, 65(5):715-731, May 1951
  - The treatment of megalo-ureter in children, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    typescript of paper by Meredith Campbell, "Primary megalo- ureter," given at the Northeastern Section, American Urological Association, Lake Placid, NY, Sep. 1951; and three drafts of remarks made by JAB after Dr. Campbell's presentation
  - Radioactive colloidal gold (Au198), 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    studies in dogs & humans; correspondence & notes, including 10 min. presentation to The Johns Hopkins Medical & Surgical Assoc. in 1953; program of Feb. 1953 meeting; draft of a manuscript, "Treatment of carcinoma of the prostate by interstitial irradiation with radioactive gold (Au198)," by R.H. Flocks, et al.; reprint of paper on colloidal gold by C.W. Sheppard, et al.; photographs, some mounted; x-rays
  - "Cytologic examination of semen", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    reprint & mounted illustrations of article by Irwin N. Frank, JAB, James E. Segerson, Fertility and Sterility, 5(3):217-226, May-Jun. 1954
  - "Urolithiasis", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    reprint of short article by JAB for Current Therapy for 1954, p. 439- 441
  - References, cinefluorography, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    scripts to accompany films; notes, references, etc.
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    typescript, reprint & some illustrations of an article by JAB et al., "Observations on ureteral obstruction and contractility in man and dog," Journal of Urology, 75(1):25-42, Jan. 1956; also, typescript of "The use of x-ray cinematography in urological studies," by JAB; also, "Cinefluorographic (x-ray motion pictures) studies of urethral, bladder, and ureteral function in man and dog, under normal and abnormal conditions"; galley proofs of a set of illustrations; handwritten list of number of cases of cine-cystograms, IUP's and retro-pyelograms, 1961-1968
  - Miscellaneous meetings, 1955,1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    program of a meeting of sections of the Academy of Medicine, Toronto, listing an invited talk by JAB: "The use of x-ray motion picture to study bladder and urethral function in man and dog," 1955; Bulletin of the Fulton County Medical Society, Atlanta, GA,32(3): March 6, 1958 with cover portrait of JAB, who had been guest speaker at the Society's 53rd anniversary banquet
  - "Treatment of tumors of the testis", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    reprint & illustrations from the New York State Journal of Medicine, 56(2):266-269, Jan. 1956 in a series called "Treatment of Cancer," plus cover letters and three 5x7" photos of an unclothed male infant; the reprint is heavily edited in ink by JAB
  - "Urgency and urge incontinence", 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    preliminary & final drafts plus author proofs & reprint of an article by JAB for Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology, 6(1):146-153, Mar. 1963; correspondence; typed copies & extracts from various published papers, and one reprint on urofluometry; typed and handwritten notes
  - "Cinefluorographic studies of the bladder and urethra in women. I. Urethrovesical relationships in voluntary and involuntary urination", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    reprint of article by Curtis J. Lund, JAB, et al., plus photos used as illustrations in this and other articles; see also Box 2-F30 for another copy and Box 2-F18 for the typescript
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    summaries of papers presented at the International Symposium on the Biology of Pyelonephritis, Henry Ford Hospital, Oct. 8-10, 1959; a review of the utility of percutaneous renal biopsies; reprint of a paper from Science, 1957, on action of antigen & other smooth- muscle stimulants
  - Materials for Ballanger Memorial Lecture, AUA Southeastern Section, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    the presentation was titled: "The use of x-ray cinematography in urological studies," presented Jan. 15, 1958 in Hollywood, FL; materials include: an announcement of the meeting; abstract and typescript of the presentation, plus an enumeration of the film segments shown; correspondence; reprints; typescripts of "Cine-fluorographic studies of the bladder and urethra in women"; essentially the same presentation was given to the Fulton County Medical Society meeting on Jan. 9, 1958, under the title: "Recent developments in visual education"; the program and newspaper cuttings are enclosed; also, a short biographical sketch of JAB
  - Miscellaneous research materials, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    typescript drafts, proposals and reports, focused on presentations at (according to notes on original folder): American Urological Association Southeastern Section (James Picker Foundation Ballanger Lecture), 1958; New England Section, American Urological Association, 1958; Johns Hopkins University Class-of-1934 reunion, 1959; American Urological Association, New York City, 1959; much of the work concerns cinefluorography (x-ray motion pictures) of the urinary system in man and dog. Also included are: hand-written notes; two patient pathology reports from Strong Memorial Hospital, Rochester; handout and notes for a Pediatric Grand Rounds presentation by JAB; a reprint order for a Benjamin article; twelve letters from the Urologists' Letter Club, 1968-1961; ca. twenty abstracts from World Radiology Current Abstracts, 1959-1961; two Journal of Urology reprints, by Richard C. Donnelly & William L.F. Ferber, and by H.H. Flocks and D. Culp; see also Box 2-F18 & F16 [RESTRICTED]
  - Book on ureter, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    untitled outline; extensive bibliographic references, mostly typed; handwritten notes; reprints by various authors; typed extracts, copies, and translations of articles by various authors
  - Panel on "Urologic Endocrinological Conditions in Children", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    material for presentation at the Clinical Congress of the American College of Surgeons, Atlantic City, Sep. 30, 1959: correspondence, notes, summaries & reprints of background publications; includes correspondence about a patient; also, preliminary program for an Intersexuality Panel including JAB at the annual meeting of the Society for Pediatric Urology, May 1969[RESTRICTED]
  - Atlas of Pediatric Surgery, McGraw-Hill, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    correspondence with Robert R. White (editor-in-chief); committee minutes, projections of illustrations, handwritten notes; successive versions of chapters in JAB's section, "Urology"; notes and text in typescript; one slide, reproduced from Journal of Anatomy
  - "Urolithiasis", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    reprint of short article by JAB for Current Therapy for 1959, p. 372- 373
  - "Cinefluorographic analysis of the bladder neck function", 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    abstract by Harold H. Borgstedt, JAB, Frank L. Campeti, & James S. Watson, submitted for the 1961 annual meeting of the American Urological Association; also submitted for the program was a cinemovie with the same title; correspondence; notes & background materials; also enclosed: program for 1961 annual meeting of Society for Pediatric Urology, in which JAB was scheduled to speak on anatomic factors of enuresis in "The Leaky Child"
  - "Acute idiopathic renal vein thrombosis in infants", 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    typescript, reprint, photographs and negatives for an article by Harry C. Miller and JAB, Pediatrics, 30(2):247-252, Aug. 1962; correspondence
  - "The role of histamine in ureteral function", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    two versions of manuscript and reprint of article by Harold H. Borgstedt, JAB, and Victor M. Emmel, Journal of Pharmacological & Experimental Therapeutics, 136(3):386-392, Jun. 1962; one draft includes mounted illustrations; also, extra photos
  - "30 casi di diverticolo dell'uretra femminile studiati con la cinecistoure- trografia", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    reprint of article by F.L. Campeti, U. Meldolesi, C.J. Lund, JAB, J.S. Watson, Jr., Annali di Radiologia Diagnostica, 12:1962; see also Box 2-F42
  - "The vesical ureter-trigone-bladder neck complex: a cine study", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    by JAB, Elliot Lipchik, Elizabeth Gordon, James Watson; a list of slides and film segments; a different version is titled: "The busy intersection of the urinary tract, or, A cine study..."
  - Bibliography on x-ray cinematography, including cinefluorography & cineradiography, 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    prepared by the X-Ray Sales Division, Eastman Kodak Co.; also Supplement I to the publication, 1966
  - Urology research materials, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    focused on two projects: 1. Presidential address to Society for Pediatric Urology, May 12, 1963; 2. A chapter on "History of urologic cinefluoroscopy" to be published in an American Urological Association-sponsored two-volume History of Urology. Folder contents include: the program; three-page typed notes for the address, "The coherent urinary tract"; one- to two-page typed summaries of various articles and chapters on developmental anatomy, urology, and cinefluorography; pages from the World Radiology Current Abstracts; reprints by JAB and by other authors on these same topics; some correspondence concerning the first project; see also Box 4-F1, Box 3-F35 & F38
  - Postgraduate Urologic Seminar, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    preliminary program (from Journal of Urology, Jul. 1964), program, and Report of the Chairman (JAB); sponsored by American Urological Association & its Northeastern Section, University of Rochester, Nov. 1964; syllabus for the Urological Pathology Slide Seminar, by Roger Terry
  - "Benign prostatic hypertrophy", 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    reprint of article published in Current Diagnosis, ed. by Howard F. Conn. Philadelphia: Saunders, 1966, p. 485-486; typescripts of two versions, plus supporting correspondence
  - "The importance of early diagnosis and adequate treatment of urinary tract infection at all age levels", 1965, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    outlines of presentation to the annual meeting of the Pennsylvania Academy of General Practice, Pocono Manor, Jun. 1965 and a similarly-titled presentation at the postgraduate seminar of the Warren County Chapter of the American Academy of General Practice, Warren, PA, Apr. 30, 1966; correspondence; extensive notes, especially on antibiotics; reprints
  - "The influence of serotonin and LSD-25 on the isolated, perfused canine ureter", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    reprint of article by H.H. Borgstedt, V.M. Emmel, JAB, Archives Internationales de Pharmaco-dynamie et de Thérapie, 162(2):345- 354, Aug. 1966
  - Urology teaching rounds, 4th-year medical students, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    teaching assignment during fall trimester, Univ. of Rochester School of Medicine; student roster & portraits; typed & handwritten class notes; Urology for Students, syllabus by Donald F. McDonald
  - Innervation of the urinary bladder, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    typed summary or extract from an article by A. el-Badawi & E.A. Schenk, titled "Dual innervation of the mammalian urinary bladder," American Journal of Anatomy, 1966, and typescript of article by same authors, titled "A new theory of the innervation of urinary bladder musculature. Part I. Morphology of the intrinsic vesical innervation apparatus," Journal of Urology, [n.d.] Also, a letter from JAB to Donald C. Martin, UCLA, about an upcoming presentation, 1968
  - Cine-uro-radiography`, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    texts to accompany films, presented in 1967 and 1968, the latter at UCLA; notes & bibliography; contains patient names [RESTRICTED]
  - "Incontinence in adults: is it stress or urge?", 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    photocopy of an article in "Consultants' Corner" prepared with the assistance of JAB et al. Patient Care, pp.82-99, Jan. 1968; correspondence re. this article, an update two years later, and on another article about contrast media radiographs; two supporting reprints by other authors
  - "Sarcoma botryoides: a 7-year survival", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    reprint of article by Harry C. Miller, JAB, and Richard K. McEvoy, Journal of Urology, 101:567-569, Apr. 1969
  - "Cinefluorographic observation of the ureter", 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    presentation at a workshop on "Hydrodynamics of the upper urinary tract," Chicago, Oct. 1969, later included in a volume of the workshop published by Academic Press; included are correspondence, program & abstracts provided for participants, various drafts of the presentation text, notes, summaries of background materials; also, the program for a meeting of the Society for Pediatric Urology, Oakbrook, IL, Oct. 1969; see also Box 2-F41
  - "Cineradiographic observations of ureteral functions in man and dog", 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    reprint of chapter by JAB in: Urodynamics: Hydrodynamics of the Ureter and Renal Pelvis, ed. by Saul Boyarsky et al. New York: Academic Press, 1971, p. 77-85; material also presented by JAB at a Univ. of Chicago workshop on "Hydrodynamics of the urinary tract," Oct. 1969; mounted illustrations; see also Box 2-F40
  - "Urethral diverticulum in adult female: clinical aspects, operative pro- cedure, and pathology", 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    typescript, reprint, & illustrations of article by JAB, Lee Elliott, J. Fenimore Cooper, Lyall Bjornson, Urology, 3(1), Jan. 1974; letter from Elliot O. Lipchik to JAB, 1972; reprints of articles by JAB and other authors, 1962-1974; also a talk presented at Western Section, AUA; application for presenting paper; suggested outline for a proposed movie; for slides see Box 8-F59; for film, see Box 9- Film #2
  - Panel on x-ray [cinematography?], AMA, Chicago, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    two typewritten pages of captions for presentation, one titled "Select Cases (12 min.)," the other "Ureteral Reflux"
  - "Contour changes in the bladder, urethro-vesical segment and the proximal urethra before and after treatment of the infection", 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    several drafts, reprint & illustrations of a paper by JAB published in Journal of Urology with title: "Infection and vesicoureteral reflux: contour changes of the bladder, urethrovesical segment and the proximal urethra before and after treatment of the infection"; also, program of a combined meeting of the Society of Paediatric Urological Surgeons, The Society for Pediatric Urology, and the Section of Urology of the American Academy of Pediatrics, Liverpool, June 1973, at which JAB gave a presentation with a similar title; correspondence; notes; reprints by various authors
  - Male fertility studies, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    reprints; photocopies; some notes; bibliography on vasectomy from a monograph or chapter
  - Possible future papers, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    in a folder with that caption, two handwritten pages of notes with heading: "To do, 1973-1974"; plus an x-ray consultation for a patient [RESTRICTED]
  - "The non-surgical treatment of urinary incontinence in the male and in the female", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    three drafts of a chapter to be published in Urinary Incontinence in the Male and in the Female, ed. by John L. Berry. Springfield, IL: C. C Thomas, 1975; correspondence with Berry; letters of permission; notes; JAB reprints; other background articles; 12 photographs
  - Pediatric urology, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    notes, correspondence, and photocopied articles pertaining to two presentations by JAB: 1. "The role of the Wolffian (mesonephric) duct in developing G. U. organ systems," at the International Pediatric Urological Seminar, sponsored by the American Academy of Pediatrics Urological Section, Society for Paediatric Urological Surgeons, and the Society for Pediatric Urology, Philadelphia, 1976; program of the scientific sessions; and, 2. The Los Angeles TUR seminar, 1975
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    consist mostly of teaching [?] notes; also, one patient pathology report; reprints & photocopies, one by W.T. Pommerenke & JAB: "Coexistence of malformations of the genital and urinary tracts in women," New York State Journal of Medicine, 47(9):996-997, May 1947; two pencil illustrations of bladder and surgical approach; handwritten drafts of annual achievement report for 1975-76; program of the Los Angeles Urological Society meeting, May 1974 [RESTRICTED]
  - The Eugene Fuller Award for contributions to the understanding of the prostrate, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    two clippings announcing the prize; JAB's letter nominating J. Fenimore Cooper for the prize, plus Dr. Cooper's c.v. and supporting letter from Willard E. Goodwin; correspondence with the American Urological Association regarding the submission; letters to eminent urologists asking for support of the nomination
  - "Excessive proliferation of peripelvic fat of the kidney", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    reprint of an article by Richard S. Hurwitz, JAB, & J. Fenimore Cooper, Urology, 11(5):448-456, May 1978
  - Clinicopathological conference: "A neuro-ectodermal tumor in the bladder", 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    reprint of conference by Richard Hurwitz, et al., including JAB; Journal of Urology, 124:417-421, Sep. 1980; correspondence
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    diagrams headed "Wilms tumor study"; a page of notes headed "Record of needs to come"
  - "Wolff's duct, trigone, and urethra in the female", 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    presentation at a Resident's Basic Science Conference, Kaiser Permanente Medical Center, Los Angeles, Jan. 1986 (F. Doughlas Stephens on same program); notes; reprints by JAB and others
  - Miscellaneous items, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 11)
    -1985 items enclosed in an envelope from "Audio Visual Services" to "Education & Research, Kaiser-Permanente Medical Center": photocopied materials on Caspar Friedrich Wolff; typed pages & photographs to be made into slides; outline of "Urodynamic- pharmacological testing," by M. Jacobs
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    letter & reprints from Donald S. Coffey; holograph outline on "Fusion and ureteral duplication anomalies," by T. Johnson; MEDLINE printout of citations concerning Caspar Friedrich Wolff; other items
  - Vesico-ureteral reflux, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    materials for a projected paper, "Vesico-ureteral reflux: Douglas Stephens and Caspar Wolff"; sketches, some sent by D. Stephens
  - Miscellaneous reprints and handouts (Box 3, Folder 14)
    -1991 application for continuation of a project, titled "Health status of American men," with Gerald S. Bernstein as principal investigator and JAB as one co-investigator; reprint titled "Vasectomy and health," by many authors, with a note by Bernstein saying "Thank you for your help with this study"; "National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey," with handwritten JAB note; other reprints and handouts on a variety of subjects; program for a meeting of the Los Angeles Urological Society, June 1988
- III.RESEARCH -- HISTORICAL & BIBLIOGRAPHIC
  - III A. HISTORY OF UROLOGY
    - Reading notes, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Reading notes, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Reading notes, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 17)
      correspondence; notes on Lorenzo Bellini, Vesalius, Aristotle, Galen, Berengario, et al.; translations
    - History of uroscopy, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 18)
      notes for slides
    - Notes & miscellaneous papers for a book, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      two-page sketch titled "The development of opaque and contrast pyelographic mediums"; extensive reading notes for a proposed book variously described as "the historical background of urographic mediums and renal function tests" or "historical development of kidney pathology & diagnosis," or "historical aspects of the kidney, especially surgical"; correspondence with Dr. Claudius F. Mayer, editor of the Index-Catalogue, about proper Latin usage; correspondence with librarians & others regarding references & illustrations; correspondence with Saul Jarcho, & a Jarcho reprint; four illustrations, some mounted; continued in Box 3-F23; overlaps materials in Box 1-F23 & F24
    - Vesalius - De Renibus, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      8x10 and 7x10 photostat copies of chapter X, De Renibus, in Vesalius' De humani corporis fabrica, book V, pp. 514-517 of the 1st edition, 1543, and pp. 630-635 of the 2nd edition, 1555; 5x7 photogrphs of Vesalius illustrations, portrait, title pages, text; one item transferred to Box 4-F32
    - Extensive notes on Vesalius, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      JAB's notation on the folder was simply "Vesalius"; one letter, plus extensive notes on readings, some translations; notes titled "Vesalius - Fabrica - Kidney" for a "medical meeting" Dec. 13, 1943; reprint of John F. Fulton's "The principles of bibliographical citation," Bulletin of the Medical Library Association, 22(4):183-197, 1934
    - Kidney of a goat, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      five negatives and one positive of kidney of a baby goat; JAB's annotation on the original folder was: "Research - Vesalius - his renal dissections - dog or goat? (see Holl & Roth); goat - donated by Dr. Schwartz, 12/19/44...."
    - Notes for a book, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      bibliographic entries, hand- and type-written reading notes; two reprints, by Leigh F. Watson & by Alfonso y Emilio de la Peña
    - Joseph Zambeccari, 1942-1943, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      notes, correspondence, article by Saul Jarcho and one by Zambeccari translated by Jarcho, typed extracts from articles; drawings and notes [related to Zambeccari?], each headed "No. 1455, 11/4/43"